this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
[Music]
this is Robert bloomin I'm here at Q con
San Francisco 2009 with Phillips ilogger
we'll be talking about the Hadoop
project today Phillip welcome to
software engineering radio hi thanks for
having so please tell the listeners
something about your background sure so
my name is Phillip I'm an engineer at
Cloudera which is startup then I just
found it about just a little over a year
ago and where I'm focused on all things
Big Data and Hadoop before cloud era I
worked at Google and I worked at a hedge
fund called eShop thank you so start off
what is Hadoop
Hadoop a system for two things has two
main components as a distributed file
system that stores data it has duper
MapReduce which is a system for
processing and analyzing that data what
is the problem domain that Hadoop is the
solution for so we do problem domain is
when you're dealing with more data than
you can fit on a single machine so
usually it's certainly more data than
you can fit in a single machines Ram but
also more data than you'd want to read
you know from the disk of a local
machine it just takes too long so what
you do is you split up the problem into
lots of smaller problems have many
computers dealing with that and then so
you stitch it all back together so what
are some of the real world forces that
have driven the emergence of this
problem domain so the this problem to
mean certainly in its current
incarnation comes from the web Google
develops and that produces GFS which
would the technologies that Hadoop is
based on to index their massive crawls
of the web it's what they used sort of
make their search engine happen since
then it's come into use in a couple
other applications but it's all still
pretty heavily wet and a lot of it is
still pretty heavily web driven there's
if you have many servers they all
produce many log
and so for example a lot of companies
analyze every single click that happens
on their web page they recorded and then
later they analyze it strain stuff and
now we're seeing it emerge into more
traditional enterprise applications
stuff like Finance and bioinformatics
and those are newer uses what are the
design goals of the Hadoop project the
ultimate goal is to be able to do
processing on a large scale so to both
storage and processing you're not able
to do and how does that come out and it
comes out of being able to do
computation work that's not possible to
do on one computer just because the
given computer can only have you know 30
to 64 gigabytes of RAM and it can only
store you know 1 to 12 terabytes of disk
so being able to spread that out so that
you can do things that weren't possible
before another goal is to let users
utilize clusters of computers as if
they're just a cluster the users
shouldn't need to know super specific
details they should just say hey run
this job let me know when the result is
in and the system should take care of
splitting up that work farming it out to
a bunch of anonymous machines and bring
it back you shouldn't need to know you
know the host names for machines 1
through 17 should just say hey my
cluster is called cluster so those are
you know that's sort of the framework in
which you we think about Hadoop is it
more typically driven by large volumes
of information like logs or the core
transactional data of the enterprise
that records its sale of its good or
service
apparently it's certainly driven by a
law you know a lot of the existing stuff
is driven by logs either stuff that your
machines produce stuff that corresponds
to page views or ads displayed or clicks
it also makes sense you know in the
financial world
every time we swipe your credit card
that's a transaction it's very similar
in some sense to a click right some
users somewhere did something and I
think it'll be
useful for a lot of that sort of
transaction as well so could you give us
some of the more prominent use cases
that you're aware of or examples you're
aware of people in industry using Hadoop
so certainly Hadoop is used to build
indices left and right so this is the
the bread-and-butter stuff
there's Hadoop use to analyze you know
logs sort of figure out what's going on
on a website and Facebook based their
entire data warehouse on Hadoop and
they've built you know they've
contributed a lot of code and built up a
lot of it and they're interested in
questions like who's you know who is
using our Facebook are they using this
new feature that we just released you
know what you know did this experiment
work what things should we show people a
lot of batch processing of that sort as
well as you know batch processing that
so there's both ad hoc analysis and
there's batch processing to make the
business run so stuff like optimizing
adds computing PageRank type of stuff
that could that's the batch processing
that's part of your production workflow
and then there's ad hoc analysis of sort
of more researching stuff so how does it
dupe different than a relational
database so the the biggest they're
different beasts it's true that both of
them can store data and both of them let
you query that data in some way but
they've got pretty different
characteristics most databases are in
the domain of one computer there's a
there's several very good cluster
databases they're usually in the domains
of you know single digits computers
Hadoop tends to scale a little bit
bigger for you know you can do it on
hundreds and thousands of years there's
so that's one difference another
difference is structured versus on
structured data databases only let you
have structured data and more or less
structured processes Hadoop lets you do
either
you know it's it's less you don't have
to fit into the mold quite as much
there's some disadvantages of that and
there's certainly lots of stuff on
Hadoop that's been developed to deal
with specifically structured data but if
you're doing
you know webpage analyses web pages are
inherently sort of unstructured there's
all this messy text and doesn't quite as
much make sense to do that on a database
platform they're usually complementary
technologies there's certain parts of
your business that makes sense store in
the database certain parts your business
it makes sense to operate on with Hadoop
so how is it do different than a
networked file system the biggest
difference is some of the computation
happens on the same machines that are
storing some of the data so whereas in
the network file system you inside of
that big black box that you bought the
big storage area network box that you
bought there's probably a couple
computers and there's probably a bunch
of disk drives and you can you know
they're very good at offering your data
letting you read and write handling
multiple writers all that sort of stuff
that file systems are good at
unfortunately there's a a bottleneck of
you know what's the network pipe you
know even if you have 24 disks in there
that each can read at 50 megabytes a
second or even 100 megabytes per second
you know what's the pipe that you can
get there to that network file system so
that you can actually process your data
so Hadoop is you know lets you
distribute the computing all over the
nodes that are also storing your data
you know there's some you know there's
some technical trade-offs there they
have different the Hadoop file system is
not good for your everyday NFS workloads
in fact it's not just not good it
doesn't work it doesn't let you do all
the operations that plastics prefers you
to be able to do it's very good at
storing really really large data sets
and disparate files and then also
processing them so can you give us a
high-level view of the architecture of
Hadoop if you had to break it into the
pieces at the top level what are the
piece
sure so first of all there's two have
there's the Hadoop distributed file
system and Hindi MapReduce talking about
HDFS first the HDFS is based on GFS
which is the Google file system and
there's paper and it's a pretty simple
model there's a central machine and
Hadoop terms it's called the name node
which stores all the metadata when you
go to write create a file when you go to
rename a file when you go to read a file
you always talk to the name node get
some in from metadata about that file
this is typically pretty small this is
all held in memory and the name node
then there is a hole every computer is
running a specific server a specific
demon called the Dana node daemon and
the data and they the data nodes are
actually responsible for storing the
individual blocks of files so what
happens is to say you're writing a
gigabyte file first of all what you do
is you split that up into 16 64 megabyte
blocks each of those blocks is then
written to three data nodes not all the
blocks have to be written to the same
three data nodes blocks are you know as
you write them distribute it to three
data nodes and there's some smarts about
which data nodes a pick stitch tries to
diversify their racks it tries to
balance it out
so given file is stored in triplicate
but it's stored in triplicate across you
know with these block boundaries so
that's the that's the architecture of
GFS what's really nice is it's very
fault tolerant because if a machine dies
GFS picks up on it a little bit lazily
because people you mean HDFS yeah HDFS
and DFS are a little bit synonymous when
you're sort of close in the code so so
it's a good reliability story when a
machine falls over either because it's
disk failed or it fell off the network
or it spontaneously burst into flames
whatever happens HDFS notices the dead
block now only has two copies and it
goes and asks one of the copies to copy
that blue you know to make a copy on to
some other machine so cool you know
centrally coordinates making sure that
oh there's always three copies of the
given file so that's the
hdfs side of the story the MapReduce
side of the story there's a central
demon called the job tracker the job
tracker is sort of the scheduler for the
cluster it shares some of the
characteristics the traditional sort of
high performance computing schedulers
handle you give it a job and it goes and
to make sure that job executes now to
execute that job it farms out the work -
task trackers so usually a typical
cluster sort of - imagine a typical
cluster you have a couple machines that
are special they're well cared for you
know you you make sure that they're
they're happy and then all the other
machines are worker machines and they're
both running they're running both a data
node and that sort of lets them right
you know use their local disk and the
task tracker which lets them schedule
which lets the system schedule
computation on that on that machine one
of the cool bits is that the job tracker
is able to find out about where the data
is and so it's able to schedule
computation locally to the data so say
you have a file and since it's a big
file you know it's a say it's a copy of
say it's all of your log files for your
website for the last year you know this
is there's a bunch of files they're all
really big your website's really
important it's a great website so these
the blocks of this file are scattered
all over the system and all you're doing
is you're doing some simple record based
computation on these so what you do is
you ask MapReduce to do this computation
and it's able to schedule the
computation so that the computation
usually happens on blocks that are local
to the machine that's doing the
computation and if not machine local
rack local and that makes sort of in
terms of hardware provisioning and makes
your networking system more happy
there's more network bandwidth left for
other stuff so that's the you know
interplay between
MapReduce and HDFS HDFS is by far the
most common input and output sort of
source for MapReduce and MapReduce uses
HDFS to you know read input and dump its
output AB and what assumptions about the
network architecture does a HDFS mate
HDFS makes the assumption that
everything is local in the sense that
HTF has not a system that iran on a wide
area network across your two data
centers you're usually running it in
within a single data center and then
you're running in a data center that
whose network is good it's well taken
care of there's some redundancy because
ultimately every data node right has
might have 2 to 12 disks an aggregate
that bandwidth might be from anywhere
from 100 megabytes to a gigabyte a
second and it might be called upon to
take that bandwidth and stream it to
another machine to do some processing or
to do copies or whatever so typically
the network should be pretty good it's
you know it's certainly oversubscribed
because the economics works out that you
typically over subscribe it but the
network topology is usually pretty
strong you typically divide your system
into rax and in urdu so it's a
traditional tiered thing it's not the
only way to do it but it's it's a common
one what sort of scheduling philosophy
is the job tracker using there's
actually a couple different schedulers
in there and they're pluggable a little
bit in the code what almost all the
schedulers are doing a couple things
so one they're balancing total
throughput of the system versus latency
and the thing that's happening there is
sometimes there are tiny little jobs
that only need to do a little bit of
data it would really suck for them to be
queued up behind the job that takes a
week to run because their user would be
way happier if they ran within the next
ten minutes and not next week so there's
there's that thing that they're worried
about another thing they're worried
about is scheduling job you know
individual job tasks of the job so jobs
are broken up into tasks in each task
may have a machine that it would have
that it's data would be local on so
schedulers worried about making sure
optimizing that to make sure that their
data local tasks going on
another thing that schedulers worry
about is so you have an organization and
there are two groups and each of them
wants a 30 note Hadoop cluster you as a
CIO CTO type of purchase and say hey hey
hey why don't you guys buy one cluster
of 60 machines and share it because then
you'll both have more capacity with
others not using it we only have to do
one you know level of administration
it'll be great but people are like well
what if they're running jobs and our
jobs don't get to run doesn't that suck
for us so there's a thing called the
Fair scheduler which tries to make sure
that even though when the machine when
the cluster is idle you can use up all
of it if there's competition for
resources it can allocate them according
from some configuration that roughly
says do no worse than if there were 230
node clusters so there's there's some
work in that regard and there's actually
some really cool research work coming
out of Berkeley that deals with the
scheduler when deeps running a job where
is the resource limitation is typically
CPU network throughput or disk or does
that depend it depends very much on the
job I we've seen all of it certainly a
lot of traditional sort of data
warehousing workloads are just disk
bound because they're sort of reading
all the data doing some very simple
aggregations CPU time is you know fairly
negligible and one of the funny thing is
you can do trade-off there because if
you compress your data more you can sort
of save bytes but it'll take some more
effort time compress and if you're doing
there's some things that you're doing
that are very CPU intensive one thing
you might be using MapReduce to do is to
do some Monte Carlo simulations of
something and you're just using it to
spread out this work across thousand
machines well then your Monte Carlo
simulation is CPU bound there's phases
and MapReduce sort of the shuffle phase
which is between the map and the reduce
phase where a lot of data as to
between sort of there's N squared ish
network connections that are going on
and the data has to transfer all over
the place that phase may often be
network bound depending on your topology
depending how much data is generated
depending how many reducers there are
all that sort of thing
can you describe the failure modes that
Hadoop is designed to handle properly so
who dupe is designed to withstand the
loss of individual sort of data node
tasktracker machines so before we talked
about others there's typically you have
a whole host maybe a hundred machines
that are both data nodes and path
trackers any one of them going down
should not does not cause data loss
doesn't cause data loss and also
whatever tasks were running on that
machine the job scheduler picks up that
they failed for whatever reason you know
be it hardware failure or you know
cosmic rays whatever happened picks up
the signs that work to a different
machine the user never even knows unless
they look you know what that their job
got it you know parts of their job got
executed multiple times in part so that
failure is really well handled that's
the main type of failure if you have
stuff like network partitions
if one rack falls down Hadoop has those
smarts enter the data is usually
replicated off rack and it should be
able to recover from that but if you're
you know if you've got a full-blown
network partition there's only so much
it can do and it expects you to
eventually reconnect the network backs
that it can you bring the bring the bits
together we've been talking for a few
minutes about HDFS and the scheduling
aspects now let's pop back up to the top
level go down the other branch which is
MapReduce tell us what is MapReduce
some appreduce is a framework for doing
competition and it's a really clever
model what happened was the folks at
Google this is Jeff Dean and Sanjay
Ghemawat who wrote the paper and drove a
lot of Google's infrastructure realized
they kept doing the same sorts of things
again and they kept running into the
same problems about you know how to deal
with failure you know how to do the
network transfer and so what they came
up with was a pattern of where they
divide the computation into three phases
to which the user has to implement some
code for so what happens is in the math
phase the framework and the framework
takes care of a lot of things for you
and the map phase the framework gives
this user-defined function this map
function some data and then that
function amidst some other data and then
the framework kicks in and does this big
sort by a key of the data that the map
are emitted and then the reducers come
in and they get all the data grouped
already and sorted by this key and there
they again invoke a function that you
defined and you know then you get to do
some more processing and then the
MapReduce framework you know helps you
write that out to the output file one
other thing that's going on there is the
MapReduce framework is taking care of
all the failure conditions of how to
split up files there's a lot of sort of
stuff under the cover that MapReduce
framework takes care of for you so that
you as an applicant you know as a
developer can focus on your core
business logic analysis whatever you're
trying to do and the framework takes
care of a lot of the stuff could you
walk us through failure handling of
let's say a map an instance of map fails
sure so let's say you're you know you're
you have your job running there's a
mapper
and the machine spontaneously combusts
so the first thing well actually let's
let's say it doesn't spontaneously
combust so your process dies for
whatever reason first thing that the job
tracker typically does so the
tasktracker on that note says hey this
process died dude what's up and the job
tracker sees notices that this process
hasn't has died either because the task
tracker told it or because the process
hasn't checked in in a while there's
some heart beating going on and so says
hmmm process died okay try starting it
again and typically if the machine
didn't fail but the just process failed
it'll start again on the same machine
it'll try running maybe it'll fail again
then the job tracker says maybe it's
just that this machine sucks you know
maybe there are bad neighbors maybe
there you know there's some other
failure of this machine maybe this
machine is configured incorrectly so
then it kicks it off to a different
machine entirely eventually if there's
enough failures at some point it
triggers the overall job to fail and
there's sometimes you sort of say don't
trigger your overall job failure 90% of
the tasks complete because it's okay you
know if a machine come spontaneously
combusts usually what happens to the job
tracker notices that you know the task
hasn't been reporting any progress it
goes and starts it off somewhere else a
key part of this is that there's an
implicit there's an explicit contract
that between you the programmer who just
wrote these map and reduce functions in
the framework and that contract is hey
the framework can run your map function
on the same data as many times as you
want so if you're doing something evil
like talking to systems outside of
Hadoop you better damn well make sure
it's idempotent so you can run it
multiple times and that's okay if you
only expect so you know that's not okay
with you you don't get to do that that's
not okay with it with you you have to
try something else if you're sort of
following the contract and you're just
omitting keys to give to the you know
keys and values to give to the reducer
that's less of a problem it knows that
those keys and values that you emitted
aren't valid because they came from a
job that you know a task that failed and
so it essentially tells people to ignore
them you're starting to describe the
programming model you start from the top
and say what is the program
model what parts does the framework
provide and what parts does the
programmer provide how much work do they
have to do
so essentially the programmer has to
dwell so the traditional MapReduce
programming model programmer has to
provide two functions a map function
which takes keys and values and emits
any number of keys and values the
reduced function which takes a key and
an iterator of values and produces any
number of keys and values that's the
basic model you can implement a bunch of
things with just that there's some
complications there's things called
combiners and petitioners and input
formats and output formats we're just
not going to you know talking them yet
that's the basic model one thing that's
happened in the Hadoop community that's
really great and cool is that people
have been building higher-level
languages that take other forms of
expressing the problem instead of just
straight out implementing the map and
the reduced function and translate it
into the map and reduce functions under
the covers they run MapReduce jobs they
write essentially MapReduce jobs for you
and those frameworks are picking hive
and Mable will cover them later in this
interview but let's come back to that
because I want to talk about pinging
hive but I have another question about
the programming well it's a programmer
use whatever is their favorite
programming language to implement map
and reduce yes so the the native for
Hadoop itself the native API is in Java
and so Java has the most is in many ways
the most functional it's the highest
it's the most performant it's one of the
most commonly used there's some hooks to
sort of call out to sub processes which
can be written in any language you know
Ruby Python Perl chooser poison that let
you write a new map and reduce functions
in those languages so there's this thing
called Hadoop streaming which takes care
of this sort of wrapper that call out to
the subprocesses
and defines an API that your you know
your scripting program needs to use and
so that you know your hadoop itself
communicates via streaming through
standard out and standard air to your
program it's really easy to whip up you
know one of these streaming programs
even if you don't know Java even if you
don't want to deal with you know all the
complete you making the jar files and
all that stuff that's not as quick and
that's used it's used actually very
widely for a variety of reasons either
because people like the scripting
language is better because the
performance doesn't necessarily matter
it's not the only factor development
time is a huge factor or you know it's
more convenient more expressive and
what-have-you
there's Hadoop help you out with pushing
the jars or the scripts out to all the
nodes where the computations occur
absolutely so there's there's something
it's part of job submission it pushes
out things to all the nodes to run them
and actually uses HDFS to do that and
there's also something called the
distributed cache which helps you push
out auxilary files and they get placed
into the sort of the current working
directory of the individual tasks so you
have some exhilarate files some data
files what-have-you you can just push
them out using that and that's really
handy you hinted at this is Hadoop
entirely implemented in Java Hadoop is
almost entirely implemented in Java
actually there's a couple bits where it
can optionally call out to a J&I native
library for example there's a it can do
that it has some cooks hooks to use
native Z Lib and that's just all that
stuff is there for performance reasons
when it's there it runs perfectly fine
without any of it but typically if
you're running on Linux you also compile
the native libraries and use that as
hadoop support it on any operating
system that has a JVM Hadoop is mostly
used on the UNIX es so it's very heavily
used on Linux I think there's a good
amount of FreeBSD usage there's some
Solaris usage a bunch of the Hadoop
developers use OS 10 sometimes so it
works on all those systems it works it
tends to work as a client on Windows and
but the almost nobody is running at
nobody that I know of is running it
served the servers
on Windows so I'm not nobody would
object to working yeah but it's it's
open-source and so as far as I know it
doesn't work out of the box and Windows
is there art of tuning Hadoop cluster to
run your job efficiently there's
definitely an art to making sure that
there's some parameters there's plenty
of knobs more knobs then than there
ideally there would be I'd say and so
there's there's definitely an art to it
you get better and better at it over
time and there's some some things like
counters that I do pass that tell you a
lot about your job and then you can use
some quick back of the envelope
calculation let's figure out sort of
what's going on could you give me a
either a war story or just a classroom
tutorial if somebody called you and say
my dupe job is running too slow what are
the first few things you're going to
look at sure so the first thing you look
at is you look at the counters and see
how many bytes it read and you sort of
take the number of bytes it read divided
by 50 megabytes per second and compare
that to the job time and if it's reading
you know let's say this job read 200
megabytes this is a bad example so let's
let's say it read 200 gigabytes you
would expect that to take 400 seconds if
that's roughly what it's taking okay
it's this pound that's what's going on
so if that's not what it's taking you do
some deeper analysis you want to figure
out whether sort of things are
configured with the right amount of
memory you uh ideally your cluster is
configured with some sort of monitoring
framework like angly or something so you
look at the CPU should you look at the
memory usage you see if the machine's
swapping you see if the disks are full
take a look at your network graphs so
slowly there's some holistic stuff you
can use some sort of there's some
support for profiling there is some
times you debug the job and figure out
whether it's doing something stupid
typically what you do is look at the job
a little bit globally and then you try
to reproduce it on small sets of data in
sirs
do you want to do optimizations you just
want to do them in small amounts of data
and see what you can do
does anyone in the community or
commercially contributed anything like a
dashboard or a Hadoop analytics to help
with the process of archeology yes and
no there's there's some products that
are helping people both develop Hadoop
Hadoop applications and sort of monitor
Hadoop clusters and that sort of thing I
work on one of them called cloud era
desktop which lets you interact with
your Hadoop cluster from a web interface
and you get to look at you know some
state about what the different machines
are doing you get to look on all these
job details that are you know pretty
easily available there's not there's not
yet a magical you know magic 8-ball your
magic crystal ball that tells you
exactly what's wrong with your program
probably there won't never will be
there's definitely space for better
tools to tell you more information about
your programs let's come back to pig and
hive let's start with pig what is pig
pig so Pig is one of the higher-level
languages developed to write MapReduce
programs without writing the map and the
reduced functions it it's a little bit's
so it was developed at Yahoo and it's
used very heavily by you know within the
yahoo organization and in other places
to do a lot of their Map Reduce
processing it's a data flow language so
you sort of declare variables that are
you know datasets and there's grouping
and there's some join operators it's a
little bit if you're a database person
it's a little bit more like specifying
the logical plan then it is specifying
the queries it's less declarative and
more dataflow it's a you know in a short
number of words and sort of a few lines
you could save yourself quite a few
lines of Java and that's partially
because Java is boilerplate and
partially because they
has some really expressive operators so
that's a big international what would be
a typical yeast case you can do many of
the things that you know lots of
counting and aggregation Pig is a really
good fit for because it'll have the
built-in operators to do some of the
counting and it'll have sort of group
buys and that sort of thing
tell us about hi so hi EV is a different
approach to a higher level languages
than Pig it's developed at Facebook for
their sort of data warehouse and what it
does it exposes sort of a sql-like shell
so you write statements that look a lot
like SQL and it keeps track of a mapping
between files and sort of schemas so did
you tell it about certain files that are
on your filesystem and what those files
look like sort of in a columnar fashion
and then you're right query you know you
write queries and those queries
themselves get run as MapReduce jobs
both pig and hive in many ways are doing
the same things and there's actually
some efforts to make Pig you know more
to make Pig also support sql-like
queries to sort of add that part of the
equation to it both of them have
optimizers and both of them are capable
of running jobs that span multiple
MapReduce jobs so you can't you know if
you want to do a map and a reduce and
then another map and then another reduce
that requires to map to Hadoop MapReduce
jobs and that's fine that's not a not a
problem well you just submit one after
you know the second one after the first
one finishes and both Hadoop and pig you
know use that to sort of do more
complicated things that can't be
expressed in a single MapReduce it would
be a Kurd say hive is language it
provides higher level abstractions on
top of Hadoop that then compiles down or
interprets down to series of MapReduce
jobs
that's accurate to say about both hymen
think they're both higher-level
languages that both affect its MapReduce
programs so the data warehouse engineer
or the sequel programmer is going to be
maybe more comfortable with the
interface that looks like hive or Pig
than was writing map and reduce jobs in
Java right I mean it takes a lot of for
certain tasks it takes a lot of the
repetitiveness out even for the well
seasoned Java developer it also exposes
Hadoop to a bunch of - entire classes of
users that aren't as don't want to be in
the weeds with with Java programming
they just want to write a quick little
thing and so it's you know it's like any
other high-level language you lose some
flexibility you lose some insulin oh you
lose some insight into what's going on
optimization wise but you get fewer
lines for for your expressiveness can
you tell us about or some of the other
more prominent sub projects in the
Hadoop ecosystem sure so there is the
Hadoop distributed file system HDFS and
Hadoop MapReduce both of these build a
lot on this project called Hadoop common
those of those used to be all one
project so that's one thing hive and pig
are both sub projects there we just
talked about them they're the
higher-level languages zookeeper is a
set of you know as a system and a set of
primitives for coordination amongst
processes they let you do sort of master
election and coordinate that sort of
thing across processes that's a that's
also a Hadoop sub project also largely
developed by folks at Yahoo there is
HBase which is a clone of another Google
system called BigTable which is a
distributed key-value store you know so
you you put these in and you get you
know you get values out and it manages
that for you it has a whole bunch of
servers and it uses HDFS underneath how
about scoop scoop is not technically a
sub project
to contributed in module in Hadoop
MapReduce so scoop is this component
this program that was actually developed
by a co-worker of mine at Cloudera and
Darren Kimball which lets you extract
data out of a database into HDFS uses
you know can use JDBC or can use some
sort of more optimized things to do so
the point is why would you do this
you've already got it in the database
isn't the database more expressive often
what you want to do is you've got some
stuff in the database already and then
you've got this huge stream of other
stuff and you need to reference one or
the other you know as you're processing
and so this lets you perhaps synchronize
parts of the data that you have in your
database that you really need you know
with you know into this other framework
where you're doing some other processing
so I might use scoop to import a bunch
of user records and then I could use
hive to join some of the data and the
user records to data in my log file some
yeah exactly I spent a little time
looking at zookeeper as far as I could
tell it's not built on top of HDFS it's
just an independent piece of
functionality is that correct that's
right I mean it's an it's in the Hadoop
umbrella because Hadoop is all about
software that makes sense for cluster
computing and so it's one of the
components that if you're for certain
applications you know if you want to do
coordination of a bunch of processes
zookeepers might used typically what
you'd use it for small bits of data as
opposed to sort of the massive amounts
that Hadoop deals with with small bits
of data you can do more expensive
consensus protocols what size clusters
are people running Hadoop on that varies
the biggest are probably a Yahoo Yahoo
has I believe more than 25,000 machines
but that's split into actually many
clusters think their largest clusters
are in the two to four thousand range I
think closer to 2000 but my numbers
could be a little off then there's
plenty other users who are using you
know hundreds
and then there's lots of people who are
using tens and lots of people who are
using one so one is the development use
case where you're running it in your
laptop you're exploring it's not a
practical case because almost certainly
you could do it you know you could lose
the overhead and do things just faster
with normal stuff but if you want to
have your things scale nicely when you
get you know ten machines when you
convince your boss that this is the way
to go these are much interest in
building Hadoop clusters on cloud
infrastructure there is I mean so cloud
era itself has some scripts that you can
get on our website which let you start a
Hadoop cluster on ec2 Montera back down
and it's really really useful for you
know experimentation early phase stuff
as you you know you use it more you
might you know you might stick with ec2
or you might sort of move in-house
depends on whether you're the other
infrastructure is and it depends on you
know cost and all sorts of things so
there's lots of people using Hadoop on
ec2 and there's you know and every other
sort of cloud infrastructure provider
definitely I had 50 node cluster in my
IT department then I would run my Hadoop
job on 50 node cluster but if I was
gonna run a job once in a while on a
cloud it's not clear to me how many
nodes and perhaps I want to minimize the
amount of compute dollars I spend are
there any rules of thumb for sizing your
cluster when the size itself could be
variable I mean sure I mean it's usually
it's it depends on so usually the the
cost thing if it you know Amazon charges
by the hour so if your if your thing
runs for 10 hours on two machines well
by 20 and run it in an hour you know you
can divide by 10 so you get take 20
machines and run it in one hour and
that'll cost you the same and then
deepen the ec2 because they charge by
the hour and as long as you're a little
bit careful so that you don't get
charged double are you saying that then
total compute hours will remain fairly
constant for a particular job if
if your job is what's called
embarrassingly parallel yes if there's
other stuff going on you know it depends
on how much data you're reading depends
on you know do you need that aggregate
bandwidth of 20 machines versus one
machine there's a lot of trade-offs it's
not that up ultimately it's not that
hard I think you get a pretty good sense
of it pretty quickly so you figure out
what you're about you know what your
limiting gating factor is and you
multiply it out and there's some pretty
good back of the envelope calculations
that you can do let's talk a little bit
about the Hadoop project how is it
organized who's the sponsor so Hadoop is
an Apache Software Foundation project
which means it's open source it's open
source under the Apache License which is
a very which is licensed very friendly
to businesses it's it's not infectious
it doesn't extend to the thing so you
can build on top of it and not release
the things that you built on top of it
to the world and so that makes it
friendlier to businesses you know the
core contributors to the Hadoop project
are you know in terms of companies are
certainly right now Yahoo and Facebook
there's a couple other companies
including cloud era that have one or
multiple committers to the project and
it's run like any other Apache project
there's a you know an iPad Hadoop EMC is
project management committee there's a
set of committers committers vary
depending on the sub project also and
everyone you know there are mailing
lists there's a JIRA which is a ticket
system so there the basic flow is you
file a bug on the JIRA you say hey you
know this is not quite right and then
discussion and you know and sues there
somebody will post the patch maybe
that's you if it's small and you know
exactly what you wanted or you propose a
change that's more complicated and lots
of people chime in eventually there are
patches eventually they get committed to
the repository every once in a while
releases are rolled so it's you know
very typical Apache project can you give
us some highlights on the project
roadmap for upcoming releases
sure so it's an open source project so
it's it's reading tea leaves a little
bit about what's going on a Hadoop 21
the release that's coming soon it was
feature frozen I think a month ago he's
gonna have working at Penn support which
is very exciting
means you can write to your files more
than once you can add to them and this
is this was really important for HBase
you know long term for you know what's
called Hadoop 1.0 this is you know at
some point Apache Hadoop is going to
produce a Hadoop 1.0 version and the
goals of that are some API stability one
of the things that's exciting this
coming the line is a new serialization
framework called Avro which we totally
missed in our list of Apache sub
projects earlier which handles
serialization and our PCs and we're the
plan is to substitute Avro for Hadoop's
other RPC mechanisms and so then you can
talk to hadoop from other languages not
just Java just because you can speak the
wire protocol more clearly and it's
defined and documented and he is the
first class API
another thing that's in the pipeline is
there's a lot of work going on on
security and improving that and Kerberos
support and that sort of stuff so that's
coming down the pipeline to always
there's performance improvements always
there's API improvements always there's
new knobs and features and fun things
are there any interesting books people
who want to learn more absolutely
there's I believe three books one by
O'Reilly one by Manning one by a press
the O'Reilly one is written by one of my
co-workers at Cloudera Tom light and
it's really good
the other two are probably really would
you foresee that someday Hadoop or
something like Hadoop would be a
standard part of operating system
distributions or do you think it will
always be a separate entity that people
will run on top I do plenty mentally
runs on multiple computers so you know
whether are they're going to be standard
operating
packages for her do absolutely cloudera
already provides rpms and Debian
packages it's only a matter of time
until those packages or something
similar to them makes their way into you
know Red Hat and Debian and whatnot it's
a slow process but all software that
gets used a lot it makes its way into
all open-source software I used a lot
that's used a lot makes its way into
that you know it doesn't make sense
really to say it's who do gonna be part
of my laptop because the dupe doesn't
make sense if there's only one machine
so it's it's always going to be
something that you install and configure
sort of specific to your topology and
your set of machines
tell us about cloud era so Claude eras
start up we were founded a little bit
over a year ago and we're doing a bunch
of things we've got the cloud area
distribution for dupe which is free and
you can download which is rpm and Debian
packages for I do if there's
instructions on how to install it that
sort of stuff so you get them on our
website they're free we have a bunch of
training materials online that you know
there's videos and slides and exercises
there's a V virtual machine that has
everything configured and up and running
that you can sort of work through those
exercises with we also offer training
and certification as you know services
that we sell and we sell support and
professional services to organizations
so organizations will come to us and
we'll help them configure how to get
started
or if they're already using Hadoop we'll
help them optimize and give advice and
you know help them out with bugs in
Hadoop that sort of stuff
and we're also building some software
around Hadoop and that ecosystem and one
of the things I mentioned earlier I work
on quad Aero desktop which is more of a
UI to talk to Hindu and that's one of
the things we're building and there's
other stuff that's you know coming down
the pipeline for you know all around who
do that's going to make sense you know
within that eCos ecosystem where would
people go to get Hadoop
so there's a you know the basic thing is
go to the pachi Hadoop webpage just it's
Hadoop dot Apache org and that's the
project's central page you can you know
there's downloads and documents and all
that stuff there's also a couple
distributions so the clutter
distribution for dupes I mentioned has
rpms the Debian packages Yahoo
distribution for dupe has a source
release which is sort of the bits that
they run basically the differences
people are always patching here or there
a couple different things and that's
that's how it works people would like to
contact you how would they do that so
you can email me my name is philip with
one L at Cloudera com that's cloud
fought an era there is I'm on Twitter at
Phil's e42 so Phil's e42 and my company
is on Twitter at Cloudera and there's a
blog and all the stuff Philips a lager
thank you very much for telling us about
Hadoop thanks so much for talking thanks
for listening to software engineering
radio software engineer radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dot net if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team @ s e - radio net or if the
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot sighs music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas